Compiler Theory

It may be self-evident, or it may be surprising, depending on your level of interaction with various languages, but despite the fact that JavaScript falls under the general category of “dynamic” or “interpreted” languages, it is in fact a compiled language. It is not compiled well in advance, as are many traditionally compiled languages, nor are the results of compilation portable among various distributed systems.

But, nevertheless, the JavaScript engine performs many of the same steps, albeit in more sophisticated ways than we may commonly be aware, of any traditional language compiler.

In traditional compiled-language process, a chunk of source code, your program, will undergo typically three steps before it is executed, roughly called “compilation”:

Tokenizing/Lexing

Breaking up a string of characters into meaningful (to the language) chunks, called tokens. For instance, consider the program var a = 2;. This program would likely be broken up into the following tokens: var, a, =, 2, and ;. Whitespace may or may not be persisted as a token, depending on whether its meaningful or not.

Note

The difference between tokenizing and lexing is subtle and academic, but it centers on whether or not these tokens are identified in a stateless or stateful way. Put simply, if the tokenizer were to invoke stateful parsing rules to figure out whether a should be considered a distinct token or just part of another token, that would be lexing.

Parsing

taking a stream (array) of tokens and turning it into a tree of nested elements, which collectively represent the grammatical structure of the program. This tree is called an “AST” (abstract syntax tree).

The tree for var a = 2; might start with a top-level node called VariableDeclaration, with a child node called Identifier (whose value is a), and another child called AssignmentExpression, which itself has a child called NumericLiteral (whose value is 2).

Code-Generation

The process of taking an AST and turning it into executable code. This part varies greatly depending on the language, the platform it’s targeting, and so on.

So, rather than get mired in details, we’ll just handwave and say that there’s a way to take our previously described AST for var a = 2; and turn it into a set of machine instructions to actually create a variable called a (including reserving memory, etc.), and then store a value into a.

Note

The details of how the engine manages system resources are deeper than we will dig, so we’ll just take it for granted that the engine is able to create and store variables as needed.

The JavaScript engine is vastly more complex than just those three steps, as are most other language compilers. For instance, in the process of parsing and code-generation, there are certainly steps to optimize the performance of the execution, including collapsing redundant elements, etc.

So, I’m painting only with broad strokes here. But I think you’ll see shortly why these details we do cover, even at a high level, are relevant.

For one thing, JavaScript engines don’t get the luxury (like other language compilers) of having plenty of time to optimize, because JavaScript compilation doesn’t happen in a build step ahead of time, as with other languages.

For JavaScript, the compilation that occurs happens, in many cases, mere microseconds (or less!) before the code is executed. To ensure the fastest performance, JS engines use all kinds of tricks (like JITs, which lazy compile and even hot recompile, etc.) that are well beyond the “scope” of our discussion here.

Let’s just say, for simplicity sake, that any snippet of JavaScript has to be compiled before (usually right before!) it’s executed. So, the JS compiler will take the program var a = 2; and compile it first, and then be ready to execute it, usually right away.

Understanding Scope

The way we will approach learning about scope is to think of the process in terms of a conversation. But, who is having the conversation?

The Cast

Let’s meet the cast of characters that interact to process the program var a = 2;, so we understand their conversations that we’ll listen in on shortly:

Engine
Responsible for start-to-finish compilation and execution of our JavaScript program.
Compiler
One of Engine’s friends; handles all the dirty work of parsing and code-generation (see previous section).
Scope
Another friend of Engine; collects and maintains a look-up list of all the declared identifiers (variables), and enforces a strict set of rules as to how these are accessible to currently executing code.

For you to fully understand how JavaScript works, you need to begin to think like Engine (and friends) think, ask the questions they ask, and answer those questions the same.

Back and Forth

When you see the program var a = 2;, you most likely think of that as one statement. But that’s not how our new friend Engine sees it. In fact, Engine sees two distinct statements, one that Compiler will handle during compilation, and one that Engine will handle during execution.

So, let’s break down how Engine and friends will approach the program var a = 2;.

The first thing Compiler will do with this program is perform lexing to break it down into tokens, which it will then parse into a tree. But when Compiler gets to code generation, it will treat this program somewhat differently than perhaps assumed.

A reasonable assumption would be that Compiler will produce code that could be summed up by this pseudocode: “Allocate memory for a variable, label it a, then stick the value 2 into that variable.” Unfortunately, that’s not quite accurate.

Compiler will instead proceed as:

Encountering var a, Compiler asks Scope to see if a variable a already exists for that particular scope collection. If so, Compiler ignores this declaration and moves on. Otherwise, Compiler asks Scope to declare a new variable called a for that scope collection.
Compiler then produces code for Engine to later execute, to handle the a = 2 assignment. The code Engine runs will first ask Scope if there is a variable called a accessible in the current scope collection. If so, Engine uses that variable. If not, Engine looks elsewhere (see Nested Scope).

If Engine eventually finds a variable, it assigns the value 2 to it. If not, Engine will raise its hand and yell out an error!

To summarize: two distinct actions are taken for a variable assignment: First, Compiler declares a variable (if not previously declared) in the current Scope, and second, when executing, Engine looks up the variable in Scope and assigns to it, if found.

Compiler Speak

We need a little bit more compiler terminology to proceed further with understanding.

When Engine executes the code that Compiler produced for step 2, it has to look up the variable a to see if it has been declared, and this look-up is consulting Scope. But the type of look-up Engine performs affects the outcome of the look-up.

In our case, it is said that Engine would be performing an LHS look-up for the variable a. The other type of look-up is called RHS.

I bet you can guess what the “L” and “R” mean. These terms stand for lefthand side and righthand side.

Side…of what? Of an assignment operation.

In other words, an LHS look-up is done when a variable appears on the lefthand side of an assignment operation, and an RHS look-up is done when a variable appears on the righthand side of an assignment operation.

Actually, let’s be a little more precise. An RHS look-up is indistinguishable, for our purposes, from simply a look-up of the value of some variable, whereas the LHS look-up is trying to find the variable container itself, so that it can assign. In this way, RHS doesn’t really mean “righthand side of an assignment” per se, it just, more accurately, means “not lefthand side”.

Being slightly glib for a moment, you could think RHS instead means “retrieve his/her source (value),” implying that RHS means “go get the value of…”

Let’s dig into that deeper.

When I say:

console.log( a );

The reference to a is an RHS reference, because nothing is being assigned to a here. Instead, we’re looking up to retrieve the value of a, so that the value can be passed to console.log(..).

By contrast:

a = 2;

The reference to a here is an LHS reference, because we don’t actually care what the current value is, we simply want to find the variable as a target for the = 2 assignment operation.

Note

LHS and RHS meaning “left/righthand side of an assignment” doesn’t necessarily literally mean “left/right side of the = assignment operator.” There are several other ways that assignments happen, and so it’s better to conceptually think about it as: “Who’s the target of the assignment (LHS)?” and “Who’s the source of the assignment (RHS)?”

Consider this program, which has both LHS and RHS references:

function foo(a) {
    console.log( a ); // 2
}

foo( 2 );

The last line that invokes foo(..) as a function call requires an RHS reference to foo, meaning, “Go look up the value of foo, and give it to me.” Moreover, (..) means the value of foo should be executed, so it’d better actually be a function!

There’s a subtle but important assignment here.

You may have missed the implied a = 2 in this code snippet. It happens when the value 2 is passed as an argument to the foo(..) function, in which case the 2 value is assigned to the parameter a. To (implicitly) assign to parameter a, an LHS look-up is performed.

There’s also an RHS reference for the value of a, and that resulting value is passed to console.log(..). console.log(..) needs a reference to execute. It’s an RHS look-up for the console object, then a property resolution occurs to see if it has a method called log.

Finally, we can conceptualize that there’s an LHS/RHS exchange of passing the value 2 (by way of variable a’s RHS look-up) into log(..). Inside of the native implementation of log(..), we can assume it has parameters, the first of which (perhaps called arg1) has an LHS reference look-up, before assigning 2 to it.

Note

You might be tempted to conceptualize the function declaration function foo(a) {… as a normal variable declaration and assignment, such as var foo and foo = function(a){…. In so doing, it would be tempting to think of this function declaration as involving an LHS look-up.

However, the subtle but important difference is that Compiler handles both the declaration and the value definition during code-generation, such that when Engine is executing code, there’s no processing necessary to “assign” a function value to foo. Thus, it’s not really appropriate to think of a function declaration as an LHS look-up assignment in the way we’re discussing them here.

Engine/Scope Conversation

function foo(a) {
    console.log( a ); // 2
}

foo( 2 );

Let’s imagine the above exchange (which processes this code snippet) as a conversation. The conversation would go a little something like this:

Engine: Hey Scope, I have an RHS reference for foo. Ever heard of it?

Scope: Why yes, I have. Compiler declared it just a second ago. It’s a function. Here you go.

Engine: Great, thanks! OK, I’m executing foo.

Engine: Hey, Scope, I’ve got an LHS reference for a, ever heard of it?

Scope: Why yes, I have. Compiler declared it as a formal parameter to foo just recently. Here you go.

Engine: Helpful as always, Scope. Thanks again. Now, time to assign 2 to a.

Engine: Hey, Scope, sorry to bother you again. I need an RHS look-up for console. Ever heard of it?

Scope: No problem, Engine, this is what I do all day. Yes, I’ve got console. It’s built-in. Here ya go.

Engine: Perfect. Looking up log(..). OK, great, it’s a function.

Engine: Yo, Scope. Can you help me out with an RHS reference to a. I think I remember it, but just want to double-check.

Scope: You’re right, Engine. Same variable, hasn’t changed. Here ya go.

Engine: Cool. Passing the value of a, which is 2, into log(..).

…

Quiz

Check your understanding so far. Make sure to play the part of Engine and have a “conversation” with Scope:

function foo(a) {
    var b = a;
    return a + b;
}

var c = foo( 2 );

Identify all the LHS look-ups (there are 3!).
Identify all the RHS look-ups (there are 4!).

Note

See the chapter review for the quiz answers!

Errors

Why does it matter whether we call it LHS or RHS?

Because these two types of look-ups behave differently in the circumstance where the variable has not yet been declared (is not found in any consulted scope).

Consider:

function foo(a) {
    console.log( a + b );
    b = a;
}

foo( 2 );

When the RHS look-up occurs for b the first time, it will not be found. This is said to be an “undeclared” variable, because it is not found in the scope.

If an RHS look-up fails to ever find a variable, anywhere in the nested scopes, this results in a ReferenceError being thrown by the engine. It’s important to note that the error is of the type ReferenceError.

By contrast, if the engine is performing an LHS look-up, and it arrives at the top floor (global scope) without finding it, if the program is not running in “Strict Mode,”[1] then the global scope will create a new variable of that name in the global scope, and hand it back to Engine.

“No, there wasn’t one before, but I was helpful and created one for you.”

“Strict Mode,” which was added in ES5, has a number of different behaviors from normal/relaxed/lazy mode. One such behavior is that it disallows the automatic/implicit global variable creation. In that case, there would be no global scoped variable to hand back from an LHS look-up, and Engine would throw a ReferenceError similarly to the RHS case.

Now, if a variable is found for an RHS look-up, but you try to do something with its value that is impossible, such as trying to execute-as-function a nonfunction value, or reference a property on a null or undefined value, then Engine throws a different kind of error, called a TypeError.

ReferenceError is scope resolution-failure related, whereas TypeError implies that scope resolution was successful, but that there was an illegal/impossible action attempted against the result.

Review

Scope is the set of rules that determines where and how a variable (identifier) can be looked up. This look-up may be for the purposes of assigning to the variable, which is an LHS (lefthand-side) reference, or it may be for the purposes of retrieving its value, which is an RHS (righthand-side) reference.

LHS references result from assignment operations. Scope-related assignments can occur either with the = operator or by passing arguments to (assign to) function parameters.

The JavaScript engine first compiles code before it executes, and in so doing, it splits up statements like var a = 2; into two separate steps:

First, var a to declare it in that scope. This is performed at the beginning, before code execution.
Later, a = 2 to look up the variable (LHS reference) and assign to it if found.

Both LHS and RHS reference look-ups start at the currently executing scope, and if need be (that is, they don’t find what they’re looking for there), they work their way up the nested scope, one scope (floor) at a time, looking for the identifier, until they get to the global (top floor) and stop, and either find it, or don’t.

Unfulfilled RHS references result in ReferenceErrors being thrown. Unfulfilled LHS references result in an automatic, implicitly created global of that name (if not in Strict Mode), or a ReferenceError (if in Strict Mode).

Quiz Answers

function foo(a) {
    var b = a;
    return a + b;
}

var c = foo( 2 );

Identify all the LHS look-ups (there are 3!).

c = ..;, a = 2 (implicit param assignment) and b = ..

Identify all the RHS look-ups (there are 4!).

foo(2.., = a;, a .. and .. b

[1] See the MDN’s break down of Strict Mode

Cheating Lexical

If lexical scope is defined only by where a function is declared, which is entirely an author-time decision, how could there possibly be a way to “modify” (a.k.a., cheat) lexical scope at runtime?

JavaScript has two such mechanisms. Both of them are equally frowned upon in the wider community as bad practices to use in your code. But the typical arguments against them are often missing the most important point: cheating lexical scope leads to poorer performance.

Before I explain the performance issue, though, let’s look at how these two mechanisms work.

eval

The eval(..) function in JavaScript takes a string as an argument and treats the contents of the string as if it had actually been authored code at that point in the program. In other words, you can programmatically generate code inside of your authored code, and run the generated code as if it had been there at author time.

Evaluating eval(..) (pun intended) in that light, it should be clear how eval(..) allows you to modify the lexical scope environment by cheating and pretending that author-time (a.k.a., lexical) code was there all along.

On subsequent lines of code after an eval(..) has executed, the engine will not “know” or “care” that the previous code in question was dynamically interpreted and thus modified the lexical scope environment. The engine will simply perform its lexical scope look-ups as it always does.

Consider the following code:

function foo(str, a) {
    eval( str ); // cheating!
    console.log( a, b );
}

var b = 2;

foo( "var b = 3;", 1 ); // 1, 3

The string "var b = 3;" is treated, at the point of the eval(..) call, as code that was there all along. Because that code happens to declare a new variable b, it modifies the existing lexical scope of foo(..). In fact, as mentioned earlier, this code actually creates variable b inside of foo(..) that shadows the b that was declared in the outer (global) scope.

When the console.log(..) call occurs, it finds both a and b in the scope of foo(..), and never finds the outer b. Thus, we print out “1, 3” instead of “1, 2” as would have normally been the case.

Note

In this example, for simplicity sake, the string of “code” we pass in was a fixed literal. But it could easily have been programmatically created by adding characters together based on your program’s logic. eval(..) is usually used to execute dynamically created code, as dynamically evaluating essentially static code from a string literal would provide no real benefit to just authoring the code directly.

By default, if a string of code that eval(..) executes contains one or more declarations (either variables or functions), this action modifies the existing lexical scope in which the eval(..) resides. Technically, eval(..) can be invoked indirectly, through various tricks (beyond our discussion here), which causes it to instead execute in the context of the global scope, thus modifying it. But in either case, eval(..) can at runtime modify an author-time lexical scope.

Note

eval(..) when used in a strict-mode program operates in its own lexical scope, which means declarations made inside of the eval() do not actually modify the enclosing scope.

function foo(str) {
   "use strict";
   eval( str );
   console.log( a ); // ReferenceError: a is not defined
}

foo( "var a = 2" );

There are other facilities in JavaScript that amount to a very similar effect to eval(..). setTimeout(..) and setInterval(..) can take a string for their respective first argument, the contents of which are evaluated as the code of a dynamically generated function. This is old, legacy behavior and long-since deprecated. Don’t do it!

The new Function(..) function constructor similarly takes a string of code in its last argument to turn into a dynamically generated function (the first argument(s), if any, are the named parameters for the new function). This function-constructor syntax is slightly safer than eval(..), but it should still be avoided in your code.

The use-cases for dynamically generating code inside your program are incredibly rare, as the performance degradations are almost never worth the capability.

with

The other frowned-upon (and now deprecated!) feature in JavaScript that cheats lexical scope is the with keyword. There are multiple valid ways that with can be explained, but I will choose here to explain it from the perspective of how it interacts with and affects lexical scope.

with is typically explained as a shorthand for making multiple property references against an object without repeating the object reference itself each time.

For example:

var obj = {
    a: 1,
    b: 2,
    c: 3
};

// more "tedious" to repeat "obj"
obj.a = 2;
obj.b = 3;
obj.c = 4;

// "easier" short-hand
with (obj) {
    a = 3;
    b = 4;
    c = 5;
}

However, there’s much more going on here than just a convenient shorthand for object property access. Consider:

function foo(obj) {
    with (obj) {
        a = 2;
    }
}

var o1 = {
    a: 3
};

var o2 = {
    b: 3
};

foo( o1 );
console.log( o1.a ); // 2

foo( o2 );
console.log( o2.a ); // undefined
console.log( a ); // 2—Oops, leaked global!

In this code example, two objects o1 and o2 are created. One has an a property, and the other does not. The foo(..) function takes an object reference obj as an argument, and calls with (obj) { .. } on the reference. Inside the with block, we make what appears to be a normal lexical reference to a variable a, an LHS reference in fact (see Chapter 1), to assign to it the value of 2.

When we pass in o1, the a = 2 assignment finds the property o1.a and assigns it the value 2, as reflected in the subsequent console.log(o1.a) statement. However, when we pass in o2, since it does not have an a property, no such property is created, and o2.a remains undefined.

But then we note a peculiar side-effect, the fact that a global variable a was created by the a = 2 assignment. How can this be?

The with statement takes an object, one that has zero or more properties, and treats that object as if it is a wholly separate lexical scope, and thus the object’s properties are treated as lexically defined identifiers in that scope.

Note

Even though a with block treats an object like a lexical scope, a normal var declaration inside that with block will not be scoped to that with block, but instead the containing function scope.

While the eval(..) function can modify existing lexical scope if it takes a string of code with one or more declarations in it, the with statement actually creates a whole new lexical scope out of thin air, from the object you pass to it.

Understood in this way, the scope declared by the with statement when we passed in o1 was o1, and that scope had an identifier in it which corresponds to the o1.a property. But when we used o2 as the scope, it had no such a identifier in it, and so the normal rules of LHS identifier look-up (see Chapter 1) occurred.

Neither the scope of o2, nor the scope of foo(..), nor the global scope even, has an a identifier to be found, so when a = 2 is executed, it results in the automatic global being created (since we’re in non-strict mode).

It is a strange sort of mind-bending thought to see with turning, at runtime, an object and its properties into a scope with identifiers. But that is the clearest explanation I can give for the results we see.

Note

In addition to being a bad idea to use, both eval(..) and with are affected (restricted) by Strict Mode. with is outright disallowed, whereas various forms of indirect or unsafe eval(..) are disallowed while retaining the core functionality.

Performance

Both eval(..) and with cheat the otherwise author-time defined lexical scope by modifying or creating new lexical scope at runtime.

So, what’s the big deal, you ask? If they offer more sophisticated functionality and coding flexibility, aren’t these good features? No.

The JavaScript engine has a number of performance optimizations that it performs during the compilation phase. Some of these boil down to being able to essentially statically analyze the code as it lexes, and predetermine where all the variable and function declarations are, so that it takes less effort to resolve identifiers during execution.

But if the engine finds an eval(..) or with in the code, it essentially has to assume that all its awareness of identifier location may be invalid, because it cannot know at lexing time exactly what code you may pass to eval(..) to modify the lexical scope, or the contents of the object you may pass to with to create a new lexical scope to be consulted.

In other words, in the pessimistic sense, most of those optimizations it would make are pointless if eval(..) or with are present, so it simply doesn’t perform the optimizations at all.

Your code will almost certainly tend to run slower simply by the fact that you include an eval(..) or with anywhere in the code. No matter how smart the engine may be about trying to limit the side-effects of these pessimistic assumptions, there’s no getting around the fact that without the optimizations, code runs slower.

Hiding in Plain Scope

The traditional way of thinking about functions is that you declare a function and then add code inside it. But the inverse thinking is equally powerful and useful: take any arbitrary section of code you’ve written and wrap a function declaration around it, which in effect “hides” the code.

The practical result is to create a scope bubble around the code in question, which means that any declarations (variable or function) in that code will now be tied to the scope of the new wrapping function, rather than the previously enclosing scope. In other words, you can “hide” variables and functions by enclosing them in the scope of a function.

Why would “hiding” variables and functions be a useful technique?

There’s a variety of reasons motivating this scope-based hiding. They tend to arise from the software design principle Principle of Least Privilege[2], also sometimes called Least Authority or Least Exposure. This principle states that in the design of software, such as the API for a module/object, you should expose only what is minimally necessary, and “hide” everything else.

This principle extends to the choice of which scope to contain variables and functions. If all variables and functions were in the global scope, they would of course be accessible to any nested scope. But this would violate the “Least…” principle in that you are (likely) exposing many variables or functions that you should otherwise keep private, as proper use of the code would discourage access to those variables/functions.

For example:

function doSomething(a) {
    b = a + doSomethingElse( a * 2 );

    console.log( b * 3 );
}

function doSomethingElse(a) {
    return a - 1;
}

var b;

doSomething( 2 ); // 15

In this snippet, the b variable and the doSomethingElse(..) function are likely “private” details of how doSomething(..) does its job. Giving the enclosing scope “access” to b and doSomethingElse(..) is not only unnecessary but also possibly “dangerous,” in that they may be used in unexpected ways, intentionally or not, and this may violate pre-condition assumptions of doSomething(..). A more “proper” design would hide these private details inside the scope of doSomething(..), such as:

function doSomething(a) {
    function doSomethingElse(a) {
        return a - 1;
    }

    var b;

    b = a + doSomethingElse( a * 2 );

    console.log( b * 3 );
}

doSomething( 2 ); // 15

Now, b and doSomethingElse(..) are not accessible to any outside influence, instead controlled only by doSomething(..). The functionality and end result has not been affected, but the design keeps private details private, which is usually considered better software.

Collision Avoidance

Another benefit of “hiding” variables and functions inside a scope is to avoid unintended collision between two different identifiers with the same name but different intended usages. Collision results often in unexpected overwriting of values.

For example:

function foo() {
    function bar(a) {
        i = 3; // changing the `i` in the enclosing scope's
               // for-loop
        console.log( a + i );
    }

    for (var i=0; i<10; i++) {
        bar( i * 2 ); // oops, inifinite loop ahead!
    }
}

foo();

The i = 3 assignment inside of bar(..) overwrites, unexpectedly, the i that was declared in foo(..) at the for loop. In this case, it will result in an infinite loop, because i is set to a fixed value of 3 and that will forever remain < 10.

The assignment inside bar(..) needs to declare a local variable to use, regardless of what identifier name is chosen. var i = 3; would fix the problem (and would create the previously mentioned “shadowed variable” declaration for i). An additional, not alternate, option is to pick another identifier name entirely, such as var j = 3;. But your software design may naturally call for the same identifier name, so utilizing scope to “hide” your inner declaration is your best/only option in that case.

Global namespaces

A particularly strong example of (likely) variable collision occurs in the global scope. Multiple libraries loaded into your program can quite easily collide with each other if they don’t properly hide their internal/private functions and variables.

Such libraries typically will create a single variable declaration, often an object, with a sufficiently unique name, in the global scope. This object is then used as a namespace for that library, where all specific exposures of functionality are made as properties off that object (namespace), rather than as top-level lexically scoped identifiers themselves.

For example:

var MyReallyCoolLibrary = {
    awesome: "stuff",
    doSomething: function() {
        // ...
    },
    doAnotherThing: function() {
        // ...
    }
};

Module management

Another option for collision avoidance is the more modern module approach, using any of various dependency managers. Using these tools, no libraries ever add any identifiers to the global scope, but are instead required to have their identifier(s) be explicitly imported into another specific scope through usage of the dependency manager’s various mechanisms.

It should be observed that these tools do not possess “magic” functionality that is exempt from lexical scoping rules. They simply use the rules of scoping as explained here to enforce that no identifiers are injected into any shared scope, and are instead kept in private, non-collision-susceptible scopes, which prevents any accidental scope collisions.

As such, you can code defensively and achieve the same results as the dependency managers do without actually needing to use them, if you so choose. See the Chapter 5 for more information about the module pattern.

Review

Functions are the most common unit of scope in JavaScript. Variables and functions that are declared inside another function are essentially “hidden” from any of the enclosing scopes, which is an intentional design principle of good software.

But functions are by no means the only unit of scope. Block scope refers to the idea that variables and functions can belong to an arbitrary block (generally, any { .. } pair) of code, rather than only to the enclosing function.

Starting with ES3, the try/catch structure has block scope in the catch clause.

In ES6, the let keyword (a cousin to the var keyword) is introduced to allow declarations of variables in any arbitrary block of code. if (..) { let a = 2; } will declare a variable a that essentially hijacks the scope of the if’s { .. } block and attaches itself there.

Though some seem to believe so, block scope should not be taken as an outright replacement of var function scope. Both functionalities co-exist, and developers can and should use both function-scope and block-scope techniques where respectively appropriate to produce better, more readable/maintainable code.

[2] Principle of Least Privilege

Chicken or the Egg?

There’s a temptation to think that all of the code you see in a JavaScript program is interpreted line-by-line, top-down in order, as the program executes. While that is substantially true, there’s one part of that assumption that can lead to incorrect thinking about your program.

Consider this code:

a = 2;

var a;

console.log( a );

What do you expect to be printed in the console.log(..) statement?

Many developers would expect undefined, since the var a statement comes after the a = 2, and it would seem natural to assume that the variable is redefined, and thus assigned the default undefined. However, the output will be 2.

Consider another piece of code:

console.log( a );

var a = 2;

You might be tempted to assume that, since the previous snippet exhibited some less-than-top-down looking behavior, perhaps in this snippet, 2 will also be printed. Others may think that since the a variable is used before it is declared, this must result in a ReferenceError being thrown.

Unfortunately, both guesses are incorrect. undefined is the output.

So, what’s going on here? It would appear we have a chicken-and-the-egg question. Which comes first, the declaration (“egg”), or the assignment (“chicken”)?

Now I Can See

The previous code snippets are somewhat academic and artificially constructed to illustrate using closure. But I promised you something more than just a cool new toy. I promised that closure was something all around you in your existing code. Let us now see that truth.

function wait(message) {

    setTimeout( function timer(){
        console.log( message );
    }, 1000 );

}

wait( "Hello, closure!" );

We take an inner function (named timer) and pass it to setTimeout(..). But timer has a scope closure over the scope of wait(..), indeed keeping and using a reference to the variable message.

A thousand milliseconds after we have executed wait(..), and its inner scope should otherwise be long gone, that anonymous function still has closure over that scope.

Deep down in the guts of the engine, the built-in utility setTimeout(..) has reference to some parameter, probably called fn or func or something like that. Engine goes to invoke that function, which is invoking our inner timer function, and the lexical scope reference is still intact.

Closure.

Or, if you’re of the jQuery persuasion (or any JS framework, for that matter):

function setupBot(name,selector) {
    $( selector ).click( function activator(){
        console.log( "Activating: " + name );
    } );
}

setupBot( "Closure Bot 1", "#bot_1" );
setupBot( "Closure Bot 2", "#bot_2" );

I am not sure what kind of code you write, but I regularly write code that is responsible for controlling an entire global drone army of closure bots, so this is totally realistic!

(Some) joking aside, essentially whenever and wherever you treat functions (that access their own respective lexical scopes) as first-class values and pass them around, you are likely to see those functions exercising closure. Be that timers, event handlers, Ajax requests, cross-window messaging, web workers, or any of the other asynchronous (or synchronous!) tasks, when you pass in a callback function, get ready to sling some closure around!

Note

Chapter 3 introduced the IIFE pattern. While it is often said that IIFE (alone) is an example of observed closure, I would somewhat disagree, by our previous definition.

var a = 2;

(function IIFE(){
    console.log( a );
})();

This code works, but it’s not strictly an observation of closure. Why? Because the function (which we named IIFE here) is not executed outside its lexical scope. It’s still invoked right there in the same scope as it was declared (the enclosing/global scope that also holds a). a is found via normal lexical scope look-up, not really via closure.

While closure might technically be happening at declaration time, it is not strictly observable, and so, as they say, it’s a tree falling in the forest with no one around to hear it.

Though an IIFE is not itself an example of observed closure, it absolutely creates scope, and it’s one of the most common tools we use to create scope which can be closed over. So IIFEs are indeed heavily related to closure, even if not exercising closure themselves.

Put this book down right now, dear reader. I have a task for you. Go open up some of your recent JavaScript code. Look for your functions-as-values and identify where you are already using closure and maybe didn’t even know it before.

I’ll wait.

Now you see!

Appendix A. Dynamic Scope

In Chapter 2, we talked about dynamic scope as a contrast to the lexical scope model, which is how scope works in JavaScript (and in fact, most other languages).

We will briefly examine dynamic scope, to hammer home the contrast. But, more important, dynamic scope actually is a near cousin to another mechanism (this) in JavaScript, which we cover in the this & Object Prototypes title of the You Don’t Know JS book series.

As we saw in Chapter 2, lexical scope is the set of rules about how the engine can look up a variable and where it will find it. The key characteristic of lexical scope is that it is defined at author time, when the code is written (assuming you don’t cheat with eval() or with).

Dynamic scope seems to imply, and for good reason, that there’s a model whereby scope can be determined dynamically at runtime, rather than statically at author time. That is in fact the case. Let’s illustrate via code:

function foo() {
    console.log( a ); // 2
}

function bar() {
    var a = 3;
    foo();
}

var a = 2;

bar();

Lexical scope holds that the RHS reference to a in foo() will be resolved to the global variable a, which will result in value 2 being output.

Dynamic scope, by contrast, doesn’t concern itself with how and where functions and scopes are declared, but rather where they are called from. In other words, the scope chain is based on the call-stack, not the nesting of scopes in code.

So, if JavaScript had dynamic scope, when foo() is executed, theoretically the code below would instead result in 3 as the output.

function foo() {
    console.log( a ); // 3  (not 2!)
}

function bar() {
    var a = 3;
    foo();
}

var a = 2;

bar();

How can this be? Because when foo() cannot resolve the variable reference for a, instead of stepping up the nested (lexical) scope chain, it walks up the call stack, to find where foo() was called from. Since foo() was called from bar(), it checks the variables in scope for bar(), and finds an a there with value 3.

Strange? You’re probably thinking so, at the moment.

But that’s just because you’ve probably only ever worked on (or at least deeply considered) code that is lexically scoped. So dynamic scoping seems foreign. If you had only ever written code in a dynamically scoped language, it would seem natural, and lexical scope would be the odd ball.

To be clear, JavaScript does not, in fact, have dynamic scope. It has lexical scope. Plain and simple. But the this mechanism is kind of like dynamic scope.

The key contrast: lexical scope is write-time, whereas dynamic scope (and this!) are runtime. Lexical scope cares where a function was declared, but dynamic scope cares where a function was called from.

Finally, this cares how a function was called, which shows how closely related the this mechanism is to the idea of dynamic scoping. To dig more into this, read the You Don’t Know JS title this & Object Prototypes.

Appendix B. Polyfilling Block Scope

In Chapter 3, we explored block scope. We saw that with and the catch clause are both tiny examples of block scope that have existed in JavaScript since at least the introduction of ES3.

But it’s ES6’s introduction of let that finally gives full, unfettered block scoping capability to our code. There are many exciting things, both functionally and code-stylistically, that block scope will enable.

But what if we wanted to use block scope in pre-ES6 environments?

Consider this code:

{
    let a = 2;
    console.log( a ); // 2
}

console.log( a ); // ReferenceError

This will work great in ES6 environments. But can we do so pre-ES6? catch is the answer.

try{throw 2}catch(a){
    console.log( a ); // 2
}

console.log( a ); // ReferenceError

Whoa! That’s some ugly, weird looking code. We see a try/catch that appears to forcibly throw an error, but the “error” it throws is just a value 2, and then the variable declaration that receives it is in the catch(a) clause. Mind: blown.

That’s right, the catch clause has block-scoping to it, which means it can be used as a polyfill for block scope in pre-ES6 environments.

“But”, you say, “no one wants to write ugly code like that!” That’s true. No one writes (some of) the code output by the CoffeeScript compiler, either. That’s not the point.

The point is that tools can transpile ES6 code to work in pre-ES6 environments. You can write code using block scoping, and benefit from such functionality, and let a build-step tool take care of producing code that will actually work when deployed.

This is actually the preferred migration path for all (ahem, most) of ES6: to use a code transpiler to take ES6 code and produce ES5-compatible code during the transition from pre-ES6 to ES6.

Implicit Versus Explicit Blocks

In Chapter 3, we identified some potential pitfalls to code maintainability/refactorability when we introduce block scoping. Is there another way to take advantage of block scope but to reduce this downside?

Consider this alternate form of let, called the let block or let statement (contrasted with let declarations from before).

let (a = 2) {
    console.log( a ); // 2
}

console.log( a ); // ReferenceError

Instead of implicitly hijacking an existing block, the let statement creates an explicit block for its scope binding. Not only does the explicit block stand out more, and perhaps fare more robustly in code refactoring, it produces somewhat cleaner code by, grammatically, forcing all the declarations to the top of the block. This makes it easier to look at any block and know what’s scoped to it and not.

As a pattern, it mirrors the approach many people take in function scoping when they manually move/hoist all their var declarations to the top of the function. The let statement puts them there at the top of the block by intent, and if you don’t use let declarations strewn throughout, your block-scoping declarations are somewhat easier to identify and maintain.

But, there’s a problem. The let statement form is not included in ES6. Neither does the official Traceur compiler accept that form of code.

We have two options. We can format using ES6-valid syntax and a little sprinkle of code discipline:

/*let*/ { let a = 2;
    console.log( a );
}

console.log( a ); // ReferenceError

But, tools are meant to solve our problems. So the other option is to write explicit let statement blocks, and let a tool convert them to valid, working code.

So, I built a tool called let-er[4] to address just this issue. let-er is a build-step code transpiler, but its only task is to find let statement forms and transpile them. It will leave alone any of the rest of your code, including any let declarations. You can safely use let-er as the first ES6 transpiler step, and then pass your code through something like Traceur if necessary.

Moreover, let-er has a configuration flag --es6, which when turned on (off by default), changes the kind of code produced. Instead of the try/catch ES3 polyfill hack, let-er would take our snippet and produce the fully ES6-compliant, non-hacky:

{
    let a = 2;
    console.log( a );
}

console.log( a ); // ReferenceError

So, you can start using let-er right away, and target all pre-ES6 environments, and when you only care about ES6, you can add the flag and instantly target only ES6.

And most important, you can use the more preferable and more explicit let statement form even though it is not an official part of any ES version (yet).